Okay, let's get started with implementing the skip-gram word2vec model.
下面我们将实现 Skip-Gram Word2Vec 模型
The first thing you want to do is load in the necessary data.
首先需要加载必要的数据
In this example, I'm using a large body of text
我的文本是用维基百科文章生成的大段文本
that was scraped from Wikipedia articles by Matt Mahoney.
这个文本文件由 Matt Mahoney 提供
If you're working locally,
如果你在本地操作
you'll actually need to click this link to download this data as a zip file,
则需要点击此链接并下载 zip 文件
and we'll move it into our data directory, and unzip it.
然后将此文件移到数据目录中并解压
You should then be left with a file just called text8 in our data directory.
你会看到一个叫做 text8 的文件
So, I've already put that data in the data directory, and here,
我已经将这些数据放入数据目录中
I'm loading that file in my name and printing out the first 100 characters.
现在按名称加载该文件并输出前 100 个字符
It looks like the first section of text is about anarchism and the working class.
文本第一部分讲得是无政府主义和工人阶级
So I loaded that in correctly,
正确加载数据
and then I want to do some preprocessing.
然后预处理数据
Essentially, I want to break this text up into
我需要将这段文本拆分为庞大的字词列表
a giant list of words so that I can build up a vocabulary.
这样就能构建一个词汇表
So here, I'm going to do that using a function in the
我将在提供的 utils.py 文件中
provided utils.py file called preprocess.
使用函数 preprocess 完成预处理流程
Let's actually take a look at this code.
我们看看此文件中的代码
So here's our utils.py file and our preprocess function.
转到 utils.py 文件并看看 preprocess 函数
This function takes in some text and you can see that it does a few things.
此函数的输入参数是 text 并对 text 执行一些操作
First, in all of these lines,
首先 在这几行
it converts any punctuation into tokens.
将所有标点转换为标记
So a period is changed to a bracketed period token and so on.
“.”变成“&lt;period&gt;”标记 等等
Next, we see that it stores the number of times
然后使用计数器
certain words appear in the text using a Counter.
存储某些字词出现在文本中的次数
A Counter is a collection that will basically
计数器是一个集合
return a dictionary of words and their frequency of occurrence.
它会返回一个字典 该字典由字词及其出现频率组成
Here, we're creating a list of trimmed words that basically cuts
在这里创建一个修整字词列表
all words that show up five or fewer times in this dataset.
删除在数据集中出现次数不超过 5 次的字词
This should greatly reduce issues due to noise in the data,
这样能够显著减少数据噪点带来的问题
and it should improve the quality of the vector representations.
并且能够改善向量表示法的质量
Then, finally, it returns those trimmed words.
最后返回修整的字词列表
So back to our notebook,
回到 notebook
I'm going to say words equal utils.preprocess text,
输入 words = utils.preprocess(text)
and I'll print out the first trim 30 words.
输出前 30 个修整字词
This may take a few moments to run since our text data is quite big.
因为文本数据集很庞大 所以运行时间可能较长
Then you should see an output like this.
然后生成这样的输出结果
Pretty much the same text that we saw above,
和之前看到的文本几乎一样
only the words are split into a list.
但是将单词拆分开来并构成列表
Here, I'm going to print out some statistics about this data.
在这里输出关于数据的一些统计信息
I'm printing out the length of the text so a word count of our data,
包括 text 的长度 即字词数量
and I'll print out the number of unique words.
并输出唯一字词的数量
To get the number of unique words,
要获取唯一字词的数量
I'm using the built-in Python data type set,
我将使用内置的 Python 数据类型“集合”
which if you recall from the last lesson,
在上节课我们提到
will get rid of any duplicate words.
集合能够删除所有重复的单词
So, we have a set of only unique words in this text.
所以获得这段文本中的唯一字词集合
So, you can see that we have over 16 million words in this text,
这段文本包含 1600 万以上的字词
and over 60 thousand unique words,
并且有 6 万以上的唯一字词
and these numbers will be useful to keep in mind as we continue processing.
在后续处理数据时 会用到这些数字
Next, I'm creating two dictionaries to convert
接下来创建两个字典
words to integers and back again, integers to words.
一个将字词转换为整数 另一个将整数转换为字词
This is our usual tokenization step.
这是常见的标记化步骤
This is again done with a function in the utils.py file, create lookup tables.
在 utils.py 文件中使用函数 create_lookup_tables 完成这一步骤
So, let's take a look at what this function is doing.
我们看看这个函数的作用
So, this function takes in a list of words in a text and it returns
此函数的输入参数是一个文本字词列表并返回两个字典
two dictionaries that map from our vocabulary to integer values and back.
这两个字典将词汇表映射到整数值并将整数值映射到词汇表
You may notice an interesting use of counter here.
这个计数器比较有意思
First, this is creating a sorted vocabulary.
首先创建一个排过序的词汇表
So this is a list of words from most to least
这是一个按字词频率升序排列的字词列表
frequent according to the word counts returned by counter.
排序依据是计数器返回的字词数量
Then integers are assigned in descending frequency order.
然后按照频率降序顺序分配整数
So the most frequent word like B is given the integer 0,
所以最常见的字词 B 对应的整数是 0
and the next most frequent is 1 and so on.
第二常见的字词对应 1 以此类推
So in our notebook, this function returns are two dictionaries.
所以这个函数会返回两个字典
Once we have those, the words are then converted to
获得这两个字典后
integers and stored in the list into words.
将字词转换为整数并存储在 int_words 列表中
I'll print out the first 30 tokenized words here just to check that they make sense.
我将输出前 30 个标记化的字词 看看是否合理
So, if we look at these values and back to our list of words above,
看看这些值 再看看上面的字词列表
we'll be able to see that 'the' and 'of'
会发现“the”和“of”
are some of the most common words in our dictionary.
是字典中最常见的几个字词
We can see that 'the' is tokenized as the integer 0,
“the”对应的整数是 0
and it looks like 'of' is the next most frequent word tokenized as 1.
“of”是第二大常见字词 对应的整数是 1
We have over 60,000 words in our vocabulary,
词汇表中有 60,000 个以上的字词
so all of these token value should be integer values in that range.
所以所有这些标记值应该是 0 - 60,000 范围的整数值
Now, our goal is to implement word2vec,
我们的目标是实现 word2vec
which relies on looking at the context around a word of interest.
word2vec 会查看目标字词的上下文
We want to define our context very carefully,
我们必须好好地定义上下文
basically looking at a window of the most relevant words around a word of interests.
并查看目标字词周围最相关的字词
There are some words that are almost never
某些字词几乎永远不会相关
going to be relevant because they're so common,
因为它们太常见了
words that show up anywhere and really often such as the, of, and for.
这些字词出现频率非常高 例如“the”、“of”、“for”
These don't provide much context to other nearby words.
它们不能提供上下文信息
So if we discard some of these common words,
如果丢弃这些常见的字词
we can remove some noise from our data, and in return,
就能消除数据中的噪点
get faster training and better vector representations.
并且提高训练速度和改善向量表示法的质量
This process is called subsampling.
这个流程称为二次抽样
This will be your first task.
你的第一个任务是二次抽样数据
Subsampling works like this.
简单说下二次抽样的原理
For each word wi in our training set,
对于训练集中的所有 wi
you want to discard it with a probability given by this equation.
我们将根据公式算出其丢弃概率 然后做出丢弃的决定
The probability of discarding a word w is equal to
这个公式为
1 minus the square root of t over that words frequency,
1 减去 t 除以字词频率的平方根
and t is the threshold value that we set.
t 为我们设置的阈值
So say, we're thinking of discarding the word 'the', word index 0.
例如 我们要丢弃索引为 0 的字词“the”
Let's say, it occurs one million times in our 16-million long dataset.
假设它在有 1600 万个字词的数据集中出现了 100 万次
These are approximations but this is one million over
这些是估算值
16 million here the frequency of occurrence.
频率为 100 万除以 1600 万
The numerator is a threshold I've set,
分子 1*10^(-5)
which is 1 times 10 to the negative fifth.
是我设定的阈值
So, if I just run these values through our equation,
将这些值代入公式里
I'm going to get a probability of getting rid of this word 98.7 percent of the time.
得出字词丢弃概率为 98.7%
Even after discarding the majority of these inner text will
即使丢弃掉大部分“the”
still leave over 12,000 of the original one million these inner text.
依然会保留超过 12,000 个“the”
The idea with subsampling is really to just get rid of
二次抽样的作用是
a lot of these frequently occurring words so that they're not always
丢弃大量这种常见词
affecting the context of other words while
避免它们影响到其他字词的上下文信息
simultaneously keeping enough examples to learn a word embedding for that word.
同时保留足够的样本并获得这些常见词的词嵌入
So, the subsampling equation says the probability that
从二次抽样的公式中可以看出
we discard a word is going to be higher if that word's frequency is higher.
某个字词的频率越高 丢弃该字词的概率就越高
Here I provided some code,
我提供了一些代码
a threshold to start you out,
设定了阈值
and a dictionary of word counts.
并创建了 word_counts 字典
This is using the counter collection which takes in our list of encoded words,
该字典使用计数器集合并获取编码字词列表
and returns how many times they appear in that list,
返回这些字词在列表中的出现次数
and I can print out the first key value pair in this list.
我输出了该列表中的第一个键值对
So here, I can see that the word token 5233 appears 303 times in our text.
结果显示字词标记 5233 在文本中出现了 303 次
I want you to use this information to calculate
请根据这一信息计算
the discard probability for each word in our vocabulary,
词汇表中每个字词的丢弃率
then use that to create a new set of data train words,
然后创建新的数据集 train_words
which will basically be our original list of
该数据集基本上和原始字词列表一样
int words only with some of our most frequent words discarded.
但是丢弃了一些最常见的字词
This is more of a programming challenge rather than
这道练习不算深度学习练习
a deep learning task but preparing data is an important skill to have,
其实是编程挑战 准备数据是很重要的技能
so try to solve this task,
试试这道练习吧
and next, I'll show you my solution.
接下来我会讲解我的实现方式